<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://huangjunye.github.io//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://huangjunye.github.io//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-06-22T10:44:35+00:00</updated><id>https://huangjunye.github.io//feed.xml</id><title type="html">Huang Junye</title><subtitle>Quantum Developer Advocate at IBM Qiskit</subtitle><entry><title type="html">From Qiskit Camp to Qiskit Hackathon @ Singapore</title><link href="https://huangjunye.github.io//2019/10/from-qiskit-camp-to-qiskit-hackathon-at-singapore.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Qiskit Camp to Qiskit Hackathon @ Singapore" /><published>2019-10-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-10-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://huangjunye.github.io//2019/10/from-qiskit-camp-to-qiskit-hackathon-at-singapore</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://huangjunye.github.io//2019/10/from-qiskit-camp-to-qiskit-hackathon-at-singapore.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/qiskit_hackathon_sg/group_photo.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Qiskit Hackathon @ Singapore Participants and Organizers&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Qiskit Hackathon @ Singapore Participants &amp;amp; Organizers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last weekend (11–12 Oct), over 40 participants had great fun hacking in Singapore with IBM Qiskit coaches from Tokyo and New York. This was the first ever community-driven Qiskit hackathon, organised by Evon Tan (CQT), Anurag Saha Roy and myself with technical support from IBM Qiskit team. The event was held at the Centre for Quantum Technologies (CQT).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to read about the nitty-gritty of the hackathon, check &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/qiskit/roundup-of-qiskit-hackathon-singapore-de651921f2cd&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; written by Anurag. Also, look out for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quantumlah.org/about/highlight/2019-10-hackathon-quantum-coding&quot;&gt;coverage of the hackathon&lt;/a&gt; at CQT’s website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will start this post by sharing my personal journey, that took me, in a matter of months, from being a participant of the first Qiskit Camp to becoming an organiser of the first community-organised Qiskit Hackathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;qiskit-camp-birth-ofqpong&quot;&gt;Qiskit Camp: birth of QPong&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first came to know about Qiskit and Qiskit Camp from Hanhee Paik (IBM Research) when she came to CQT’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://cqt11.quantumlah.org/&quot;&gt;annual symposium&lt;/a&gt; in Jan 2019. Hanhee helped me get the invitation to the Qiskit Camp held in Vermont, US soon afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the Qiskit Camp last March, I had no experience in software or game development. During the Camp, I formed a team with Jarrod Reilly and Anastasia Jeffery (both from University of Colorado Boulder). Together we made a quantum version of the classic video game Pong, called &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/HuangJunye/QPong&quot;&gt;QPong&lt;/a&gt;, with mentorship by one of the Qiskit coaches, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/JavaFXpert&quot;&gt;James Weaver&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, QPong has been &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/JavaFXpert/status/1114626404778426370&quot;&gt;demoed in a museum&lt;/a&gt;, ported to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/HuangJunye/status/1172196396721532928&quot;&gt;IBM Quantum Arcade machine&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a1NZC5rqQD8&amp;amp;list=PLOFEBzvs-Vvp2xg9-POLJhQwtVktlYGbY&quot;&gt;featured on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;. It even got me &lt;a href=&quot;https://indico.cern.ch/event/838035/&quot;&gt;an invitation to CERN&lt;/a&gt;. Now, some call me the “QPong guy”!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;iframe-container&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe id=&quot;frame&quot; width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/a1NZC5rqQD8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can imagine, the unexpected journey after the Camp has completely changed my career. I will write more about it in a separate article. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-power-of-twitter-the-beginnings-of-the-hackathon&quot;&gt;The power of Twitter: the beginnings of the Hackathon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Camp, I kept thinking about bringing that amazing experience to students in Singapore who might not have had the chance to attend any Qiskit Camp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around May, I contacted Suzie Kirschner, the Qiskit Global Event Lead, to discuss a potential Qiskit Hackathon. But the planning really kicked off after I saw a tweet by Anurag, then a Research Assistant at the CQT, making a petition to host a Qiskit Hackathon in Singapore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet tw-align-center&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Never underestimate the power of a tweet. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/qiskithackathonsg?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#qiskithackathonsg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;12 hours to go now&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/HuangJunye?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@HuangJunye&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/quantumlah?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@quantumlah&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Bingmanson?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@Bingmanson&lt;/a&gt; @veenaiyuri &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/qiskit?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@qiskit&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/LEQTJs2OAO&quot;&gt;https://t.co/LEQTJs2OAO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Anurag Saha Roy (@anuragsaharoy) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/anuragsaharoy/status/1182277725022609409?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;October 10, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then teamed up and quickly got the support from both CQT and Qiskit. With the expert guidance of Evon Tan from CQT, Yuri Kobayashi and Brian Ingmanson from Qiskit, the planning moved on quickly. And the rest is history (that you can read &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/qiskit/roundup-of-qiskit-hackathon-singapore-de651921f2cd&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quantumlah.org/about/highlight/2019-10-hackathon-quantum-coding&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;qiskit-hackathon--singapore-lessonslearnt&quot;&gt;Qiskit Hackathon @ Singapore: lessons learnt&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-good&quot;&gt;The good&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If participating in a hackathon is exhausting, organising one is on another level. Neither Anurag nor I had done it before. We had a lot to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, we had generous financial and logistical support from CQT. Special mention goes to Evon (CQT), for handling most tasks, including budgeting and logistics. The marketing strategy also worked unexpectedly well, as all the spots were filled up in less than 24 hours after the event page went live. Even though we didn’t target specific participant demographics, we eventually had a healthy mix of undergraduates and graduates with diverse backgrounds as well as working professionals from research institutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making sure there were enough learning resources (e.g. links to Qiskit videos and tutorials via email) for participants available before the Hackathon was crucial for its success. And in a situation like ours, dedicating the first morning to workshops was a wise decision, as most participants were new to quantum computing. Prof Dimitris Angelakis (CQT) gave a crash course into quantum computing at the start, followed by talks on the basics of Qiskit by Luciano Bello (Qiskit) and its many applications by Rudy Raymond (Qiskit). As for myself, I kicked off my speaking career (!) by giving a talk about making games with Qiskit, based on my experience of making QPong and the QPong Arcade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/qiskit_hackathon_sg/qiskit_game_talk.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Qiskit Game Talk&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Do you recognise who’s on my T-shirt? Yes, he is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doug_Bowser&quot;&gt;President of Nintendo of America&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-bad&quot;&gt;The bad&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though the Hackathon exceeded our expectations, there were a few things that could be improved in future hackathons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Workshops should be more hands-on. The workshops jammed too much information and did not provide opportunities for hands-on activities. If I were to do it again, I would choose to arrange 2 sessions of hands-on workshops: one on Qiskit basics and one on its applications (of course, I would go for Qiskit games!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideas pitching and team formation. The methods we chose for ideation and team formation were not effective. We used &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/qiskit-community/qiskit-hackathon-singapore-19/issues&quot;&gt;Github issues&lt;/a&gt; as a way for coaches and participants to put forward their ideas. It was very difficult to keep tracks of the team members on Github. Some teams had too many members while others did not have enough members. We should use crowdforge.io or hackathon.io for future hackathons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cultural differences. During the pitching session, organisers had to make a lot of efforts to encourage participants to pitch their ideas. The situation was very different from previous Qiskit Camps where so many people wanted to pitch their ideas that the organisers had to limit the time for the pitching sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think there are two main factors. First, as mentioned before, most participants in the Hackathon were not familiar with quantum computing before the event, whereas many participants for Qiskit Camps were students and researchers in closely-related fields. Another important factor is the cultural difference between Asian and European/American. In Asia, students tend to be shy and hesitant to express their thoughts if they are not certain about the subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, when participants felt confident in smaller teams, they were willing to brainstorm together and to come up with their own projects. All in all, 4 projects out of 10 came from participants, which was reassuring!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-ugly&quot;&gt;The ugly&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing in quantum computing is ugly, since &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IBM_Q_System_One&quot;&gt;IBM Q System One&lt;/a&gt; is so beautiful ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/qiskit_hackathon_sg/ibm_q_system_one.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;IBM Q System One&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Isn’t it gorgeous?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-experience-as-a-first-time-coach&quot;&gt;My experience as a first-time coach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from organising, I also had the chance to coach a few teams that were working on games (4 out of 10 teams!). Although I wasn’t hacking alongside them, I could go to discuss with each team regularly. This was not only to check their progress and provide feedback, but also to have some fun playing their games!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet tw-align-center&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Great team works! &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/uAjE5k0ip5&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/uAjE5k0ip5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Huang Junye 黄俊晔 (@HuangJunye) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/HuangJunye/status/1183084232232460288?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;October 12, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this process to be empowering. Even with my own limited experience of Qiskit and game development, I could help the teams to focus on the essence of their projects provide ideas for improvement. My role also entailed debugging their codes and making suggestions for their final presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I emphasised the teams to manage their expectations, which is, in my opinion, one of the most important skill for project management. One participant reminded everyone after hours of hacking with this photo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/qiskit_hackathon_sg/story-of-every-project-after-3-months.png&quot; alt=&quot;Story of every project after 3 months&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://me.me/i/story-of-every-project-after-3-months-initial-work-plan-8321639662484cf399ca13c20567379e&quot;&gt;So true!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, I was thrilled to see that most teams came up with something better than paper planes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am glad that some participants of the Qiskit Hackathon @ Singapore were invited to the upcoming &lt;a href=&quot;https://qiskit.org/events/asia/&quot;&gt;Qiskit Camp Asia&lt;/a&gt; (which will be held in Japan on Nov 18–21). I will also continue working with the teams that made a quantum game, to help them improve the projects for submission to &lt;a href=&quot;https://ibmqawards.com/&quot;&gt;IBM Q Award&lt;/a&gt;. It is crazy to think that if they got a prize, they would be invited to the Qiskit Camp next year. If that came true, I would have not only accomplished my initial goal of bringing the Qiskit Camp experience to Singapore, but also contributed to sending some students to experience the original Qiskit Camp.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="qiskit" /><category term="hackathon" /><category term="cqt" /><summary type="html">Qiskit Hackathon @ Singapore Participants &amp;amp; Organizers</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Qiskit Camp 2019</title><link href="https://huangjunye.github.io//2019/03/qiskit-camp-19.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Qiskit Camp 2019" /><published>2019-03-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://huangjunye.github.io//2019/03/qiskit-camp-19</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://huangjunye.github.io//2019/03/qiskit-camp-19.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/qiskit_camp_19/4am_club.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;4am Club&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Qiskit Camp 4am Club&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;在一个偶然的机会下，我受邀请参加IBM组织的第一届&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/qiskit/recap-of-qiskit-camp-2019-4d95f07dd179&quot;&gt;Qiskit Camp&lt;/a&gt;。这活动正好安排在March Meeting之前，所以我开会顺便就去参加了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/qiskit_camp_19/qiskit_elements.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Qiskit Elements&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Qiskit的架构&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://qiskit.org/&quot;&gt;Qiskit&lt;/a&gt;是IBM开发的基于Python的开源量子编程库。这个库包含好几个子库，名字都是拉丁语的元素，很有意思。Terra是土元素，有奠基的意思。Terra是Qiskit的基础，最基本的东西都在里头。Aer是气元素，用来模拟量子计算机。Aqua是水元素，包含很多量子算法，特别是量子化学。Ignis是火元素，用来模拟噪声和错误。官方介绍&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/qiskit/qiskit-and-its-fundamental-elements-bcd7ead80492&quot;&gt;请点这&lt;/a&gt;。最近&lt;a href=&quot;https://zhuanlan.zhihu.com/quriosity&quot;&gt;新开了一个专栏&lt;/a&gt;，打算专门写量子计算相关的文章。应该会写一两篇Qiskit的教程，虽然我也只懂些皮毛。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/qiskit_camp_19/universities.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Participating Universities&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;我大NUS的Logo竟然被放到最中间！&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;这次活动一共有135人参加，来自19个国家，48个大学，9个研究所，5家量子初创公司。我拉着实验室同学一起去。这样一来，NUS就有六个人参加，估计是所有大学里人数最多的。（所以NUS的Logo放在最中间^_^）Qiskit Camp的第一天在纽约州Yorktown的IBM J. T. Watson Research Center举行。这天的主要目的是教会所有人怎么用Qiskit。参会的大部分人都没怎么用过Qiskit，而用过Qiskit的小部分人参加自发组织的Unconference，当场提出一些课题进行讨论。IBM官方活动总结&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/qiskit/recap-of-qiskit-camp-2019-4d95f07dd179&quot;&gt;请点这&lt;/a&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/qiskit_camp_19/ibm_fellow.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;IBM Fellow&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;IBM Fellow名人堂&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/qiskit_camp_19/fridge.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dilfridge&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;唯一可以拍照的稀释制冷机&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/qiskit_camp_19/chip.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Quantum Chip&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;稀释制冷机不只是个摆设，下面似乎还装着芯片。可惜手机不给力，看不清芯片里是不是量子比特。&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;第一天的Workshop结束以后的当天晚上，IBM把我们载到300公里以外的佛蒙特州的深山雪林里的小黑屋（误）里，把所有人分成3到5人的小组，进行24小时的Hackathon。我和两个科罗拉多大学的本科生组队，在一个IBM资深程序员的带领下，搞了一个量子版的“经典”游戏《乓》：QPong。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/qiskit_camp_19/snow.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Snowy Lake&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;佛蒙特州是滑雪胜地，到处都是雪。&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/qiskit_camp_19/qpong.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;QPong&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;QPong游戏界面&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;QPong通过量子电路来控制挡板位置来把小球反弹回去。目前的版本有三个量子比特，有八种本征态，对应着挡板的八个位置。小球未到达挡板之前，挡板可能出现位置的概率用透明度表示。当小球到达挡板区域，量子电路实现的量子态被测量，得出的结果决定挡板最终位置。量子电路可以实现的量子门有X，Y，Z，Rx，Ry，Rz，Hadamard和CNOT。游戏是用Qiskit和Pygame实现的，源代码放在&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/HuangJunye/QPong&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;。运行之前需要安装Qiskit、Pygame和Matplotlib。推荐安装PyCharm来运行。如果你们感兴趣，可以一起开发这个游戏。目前游戏还是非常简陋。电脑玩家完全随机，非常地笨。未来还打算添加双人游戏、量子比特数量升级等等。也可以修改成量子打砖块，趣味性就更强了。&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="qiskit" /><category term="hackathon" /><summary type="html">Qiskit Camp 4am Club</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">APS March Meeting 2019</title><link href="https://huangjunye.github.io//2019/03/aps-march-meeting-2019.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="APS March Meeting 2019" /><published>2019-03-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://huangjunye.github.io//2019/03/aps-march-meeting-2019</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://huangjunye.github.io//2019/03/aps-march-meeting-2019.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/march_meeting_19/venue.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Conference Venue&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;会场人来人往&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;刚参加完March Meeting回来，赶紧把所见所想写下来，不然再过几天就没有动力写了。写出来的流水账还请大家见谅。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;这是我第一次参加March Meeting。今年的会议在波士顿举行。虽然事前知道这是物理学界最大的会议，但是那种庞大的震撼感只有参会才能体会到。会议一共五天，从早上8点开到下午5点半。一天三个session，每个session都有70个左右报告同时进行。普通报告12分钟，邀请报告36分钟，一天下来就有2000个报告。每个session之间只有15分钟休息时间，而从会场一头走到另一头就要10分钟。如果一直都有感兴趣的报告，那就连吃午饭的时间都没有。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;今年的会议一共有11000人参加，我感觉似乎所有物理学家都在。在会上我见到了很多在论文上看到的大牛：Philip Kim, Allan MacDonald, Ashvin Vishwanath, Kin Fai Mak, Andrea Young, John Preskill, Jason Alicea等等。还见到一些邮件交流过但还没见过面的人：Joel I-Jan Wang和Yu Saito。有天上厕所时猛然发现站在我旁边的就是鼎鼎大名的阿笠博士：好蛋爷。好蛋爷爷人很低调，拿了诺贝尔奖还来做普通报告，10分钟报告，2分钟问问题，跟博士生一样。March Meeting对于很多人来说还是同学聚会。我实验室的同学们都能在March Meeting见到很多国内本科同学。然而像我在大NTU毕业的，是不可能遇到同学的。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/qe/haldane.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Duncan Haldane&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;好蛋爷爷与阿笠博士&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;March Meeting跟我以前参加过的会议不一样的地方不止是规模，还有各种活动的自发性和多样性。70个平行session，你可以任意组合。像我这样搞二维材料的学生，听得最多的却是量子计算机报告。还去听了一个气候变化的报告和几个讲无人驾驶和飞机的报告。你也可以选择不听报告，找人讨论。整个会场里，无时无刻不能看到很多人在讨论。真是一千个人就有一千个不同的March Meeting，每个人的参会体验都不一样。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;twistronics&quot;&gt;Twistronics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;今年最火的报告是去年曹原开的twistronics坑。现在发现，除了两张单层石墨烯扯一下可以超导，两张双层石墨烯、ABC三层石墨烯+氮化硼、硒化钨WSe2扯一扯也能超导。曹原这么一扯，就给二维材料续命至少5年。二维材料从石墨烯开始，搞了几年以后，发现其他二维材料MoS2和各种TMD、黑磷，续命好几年。单种材料搞得差不多以后发现可以把一种材料放到另一种材料上，排列组合层出不穷，又续命好几年。去年这么一扯，又增加了一个自由度。可以想象在不久将来，我们会看到五六层材料扯出不同角度，实现各种神奇现象。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;目前来说，这些实验难度非常高，搞实验的组屈指可数，只有动手能力最强的几个组有这个能力：Pablo Jarillo-Herrero, Philip Kim, Andrea Young, Cory Dean, Feng Wang等等。搞理论的人倒是非常多。之前搞拓扑材料起家的人似乎都来高twisted系统了：傅亮、Ashvin Vishwanath, Andrei Bernevig等等。当然也有一些老牌的大牛：Allen MacDonald, Sanker Das Sarma, Francisco Guinea等等。今年早些时候在UCSB的&lt;a href=&quot;http://online.kitp.ucsb.edu/online/bands_m19/&quot;&gt;KITP开了twisted的会议&lt;/a&gt;，而且都有录像，所以March Meeting我没有怎么听twisted的talk。大部分时间我都去听量子计算机的报告。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;量子计算机&quot;&gt;量子计算机&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;谷歌&quot;&gt;谷歌&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/march_meeting_19/bristlecone.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bristlecone&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Bristlecone的错误率分布&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;谷歌的72量子比特Bristlecone量子处理器进展缓慢。&lt;a href=&quot;https://ai.googleblog.com/2018/03/a-preview-of-bristlecone-googles-new.html&quot;&gt;去年March Meeting放的卫星&lt;/a&gt;到现在都还没完成调试。今年的报告讲的主要是怎么系统性地做优化调试。Julian Kelly一月时来新加坡讲的就是这些，没有什么新的信息。谷歌愿意放长线钓大鱼，为以后更大的量子计算机慢慢打好基础的做法应该鼓励，只是公关部门提早放卫星导致现在大家心里落差很大。量子霸权估计还要好几年才能实现。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ibm&quot;&gt;IBM&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/march_meeting_19/quantum_volume.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Quantum Volume&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;量子摩尔定律&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;很明显IBM被去年谷歌放卫星惹得坐不住，今年也来放卫星。首先今年早些时候发布槽点满满的全球第一台商用通用量子计算机&lt;a href=&quot;https://newsroom.ibm.com/2019-01-08-IBM-Unveils-Worlds-First-Integrated-Quantum-Computing-System-for-Commercial-Use&quot;&gt;System One&lt;/a&gt;。这量子计算机性能比手机还弱，价值上千万，唯一的亮点是好看。然后March Meeting期间在IBM博客上&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ibm.com/blogs/research/2019/03/power-quantum-device/&quot;&gt;发表文章&lt;/a&gt;，宣称System One的量子体积（Quantum Volume，IBM提出的一个衡量量子计算机算力的标准）达到新高度。过去几年IBM的量子处理器的量子体积进步速符合摩尔定律，并由此提出“量子摩尔定律”。三个数据点就推出规律胆子真大。不过当年摩尔也是四个数据点就提出这个大胆的猜想。当然摩尔定律是一个人为的定律，一开始是猜想，后来变成了指导行业发展的方向标。摩尔定律神奇的地方不在于其准确性，而在于半导体行业能够长时间持续实现这个目标。IBM放的另一个卫星是500微秒的退相干时间，大概是之前的5倍。报告里只放了一个图，没有解释怎么能达到如此长的退相干时间。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rigetti&quot;&gt;Rigetti&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rigetti的报告刚好都和其他我感兴趣的报告冲突了，没有去听。但听说今年很风光，全方面提高了量子比特的退相干时间，&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1901.08042&quot;&gt;达到100微秒级别&lt;/a&gt;，两量子比特门的保真度达到99%。Rigetti去年放卫星说要造128量子比特的量子处理器，真是水平越低吹的牛越大。不过作为初创公司能跟谷歌、IBM这样的大公司对着干，实在不得不佩服。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;英特尔&quot;&gt;英特尔&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/march_meeting_19/intel_bluefors.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Intel BlueFors&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;低温高速自动测量系统&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;英特尔在今年的March Meeting展示了它的工业实力。它认为量子计算机的两大瓶颈在于：实验反馈回路太慢和量子比特的接线太多。英特尔认为没有必要在乎100个量子比特的问题，只在乎100万个量子比特的问题。当然这是因为它远远落后于谷歌和IBM，不得不另辟曲径。在英特尔眼里，量子比特就是晶体管（英特尔主打硅自旋量子比特）。他们打算用造晶体管的那套方法来造量子比特。一方面建立常温测量和低温测量的相关性，通过常温测量高速大量筛选优良器件进行低温测量，从而大大提高开发的速度。另一方面，它和Bluefors、Afore合作&lt;a href=&quot;https://newsroom.intel.com/news/intel-drives-development-quantum-cryoprober-bluefors-afore-accelerate-quantum-computing/#gs.0k0x47&quot;&gt;开发低温高速自动测量系统&lt;/a&gt;，提高低温测量的速度。接线方面，他们在门电路、芯片、整个系统三个层次进行优化，减少接线。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;微软&quot;&gt;微软&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;在这几家公司里，微软的进度是最慢的。微软跟谷歌类似，没有太多搞硬件的传统，只能靠收买大学实验室起家。现在微软投资的实验室差不多有十家，遍布全球。微软投入的资金非常大，应该比谷歌多很多，跟IBM差不多。微软的策略比较特别，它想做拓扑量子比特。拓扑量子比特在理论上可以实现非常长的退相干时间，非常高的量子门保真度。一个拓扑量子比特可以顶一千个普通超导量子比特，从而实现弯道超车。然而拓扑量子比特的基础，神奇的马约拉纳零能模仍然未能被严格证实，量子比特的实现遥遥无期。可以说其他家都开始解决工程问题，而微软仍未解决最基础的科学问题。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/march_meeting_19/majorana1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Coulomb island interferometer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/march_meeting_19/majorana2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Flux induced Majorana zero modes&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Flux induced Majorana zero modes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;从今年的报告看来，Kouwenhoven和Marcus组都在力图证明纳米线两端的零能模具有非局域的相关性，以此用来证明这些零能模是马约拉纳零能模。这些实现以后，下一步应该就是诺奖级别的实验——braiding。实现能零能模的braiding，而且能展示出非阿贝性统计，充分证明零能模是马约拉纳零能模。在那以后才能开始尝试做拓扑量子比特。这么看来五年内很难看到第一个拓扑量子比特。希望微软能沉住气，不要被其他几家公司放卫星的影响。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;签证问题&quot;&gt;签证问题&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;今年有很多人去不了March Meeting。有些人在美国读书工作，回国办续签被卡了好几个月，现在仍在国内等签证。这些人包括曹原。曹原在会议第一天第一场有个邀请报告，结果去不了，只能让实验室的同事做报告。还有很多在国内工作的中国人拿不到B1/2签证去开会，或者很迟才拿到不能全程参加会议。APS已经注意到这个问题，正在搜集数据和典型案例，计划跟国会干涉。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;最后放一张我最新抓到的一只诺贝尔奖得主^_^&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/march_meeting_19/strickland.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Donna Strickland&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Donna Strickland&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">会场人来人往</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">我印象中的张首晟</title><link href="https://huangjunye.github.io//2018/12/%E6%88%91%E5%8D%B0%E8%B1%A1%E4%B8%AD%E7%9A%84%E5%BC%A0%E9%A6%96%E6%99%9F.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="我印象中的张首晟" /><published>2018-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://huangjunye.github.io//2018/12/%E6%88%91%E5%8D%B0%E8%B1%A1%E4%B8%AD%E7%9A%84%E5%BC%A0%E9%A6%96%E6%99%9F</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://huangjunye.github.io//2018/12/%E6%88%91%E5%8D%B0%E8%B1%A1%E4%B8%AD%E7%9A%84%E5%BC%A0%E9%A6%96%E6%99%9F.html">&lt;p&gt;今天在微信上知道张首晟去世的噩耗，非常震惊。两天前我才在专栏里回忆了一下读博士这前两年做了些什么，学了些什么。里面提到我参加过的会议，其中有三个，张首晟都去了。我跟张首晟不熟，他不认识我，我也没跟他说过几句话。我仰慕他，为他做出的物理贡献感到骄傲，但同时我又对他后期分心搞风投感到不满。在这里我想写的是，在这三次会议里张首晟说过的一些东西，一般报道不会提到的一些小事情，以作纪念。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;这三次会议，分别是新加坡的QM90、西班牙的Majonext2017和清华举办的OCPA9，都在2017年。这三次会议，张首晟的报告几乎是一样的，讲的都是17年7月发在&lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/357/6348/294&quot;&gt;Science上&lt;/a&gt;的工作：在QAHI+SC结构里实现拓扑超导，并且探测到会移动的手性马约拉纳费米子。不过，在这三次报告里，可以看到这个实验的演进，后来补充的几个实验结果让论文更有说服力。不过，这个工作发表以后还是引起了很多争议，包括文小刚写了篇PRL直接打脸，详情可以看看&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.condmatjclub.org/?p=3219&quot;&gt;JCCM的评论&lt;/a&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interactive-session-with-prof-zhang-shoucheng&quot;&gt;Interactive Session with Prof Zhang Shoucheng&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/zhang_shoucheng/ntu.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;NTU&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Interactive Session with Prof Zhang Shoucheng at NTU，在IAS网站上盗了这张图&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;第一次听说张首晟，是2013年。当时我还是懵懂的材料本科生。我收到张首晟&lt;a href=&quot;https://graphene.nus.edu.sg/interactive-session-with-prof-zhang-shoucheng-at-ntu/&quot;&gt;来NTU作报告&lt;/a&gt;的邮件。搜了一下，看到Google Scholar引用两万多！这个人真牛逼！但是看一下他研究的东西：拓扑绝缘体？量子自旋霍尔效应？量子反常霍尔效应？这些名词完全没看懂，甚至连听都没听过，于是没有去听……后来阴差阳错地转到了物理，做的研究还跟拓扑绝缘体、拓扑超导体息息相关。看的文章越多，就越后悔当初没去听张首晟的报告。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;qm90&quot;&gt;QM90&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/zhang_shoucheng/qm90.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;QM90&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;张首晟在QM90会议上提到，他的QSHE工作的eureka moment，发生在11年前的这个讲堂里！&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;错过13年的报告，终于见到张首晟时，已是四年后。那是NTU-IAS举办的纪念量子力学奠基90周年的QM90会议。报告的内容上面已经说过了。这里想说的是他跟NTU-IAS的关系。在会上他表达了NTU-IAS的感激，因为他这一生最重要的工作：量子自旋霍尔效应（QSHE），要归功于06年IAS组织的&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ntu.edu.sg/ias/PastEvents/2006/workshoponspintronics/Pages/default.aspx&quot;&gt;Workshop on Spintronics&lt;/a&gt;。当时他看到Molenkamp展示出来的半导体带隙图（下图），发现HgTe的带隙居然是负值！在跟Molenkamp详细讨论以后，得到了CdTe-HgTe-CdTe量子阱的想法（&lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/314/5806/1757&quot;&gt;Bernevig-Hughes-Zhang模型&lt;/a&gt;）来实现QSHE。接着跟Molenkamp合作，实验很顺利地做进行，一年后就&lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/318/5851/766&quot;&gt;发表出来了&lt;/a&gt;。当时我听到这个故事，顿时感觉热血沸腾。没想到我的母校能跟QSHE扯上这么大的关系！瞬间自信爆棚，觉得自己也能够做出同样等级的研究（才怪）。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;majornext2017&quot;&gt;Majornext2017&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;最让我感到遗憾的是，即使一年内三次见到张首晟，我也没有鼓起勇气在会间跟他搭话。我跟他唯一的对话，是在他的报告之后问过一个问题：怎么在QAHI+SC这个拓扑超导体结构里做量子计算。他的回答很敷衍、很标准化、很不靠谱：加个磁场打开漩涡，然后用STM来操控。今年早些时候他&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/content/115/43/10938.short&quot;&gt;在PNAS上发了一篇文章&lt;/a&gt;，讲的正是我问的问题。这篇论文很靠谱，并没有用到漩涡，跟他的回答完全不沾边。这篇文章中他的贡献有多少不可得知。可能这主要是祁晓亮带着学生做的。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;听说这几年张首晟的心思都放在风投，而不是科研。这一点在Majonext2017的时候表现得特别明显。报告讲完后，Jarillo-Herrero问了张首晟好几个问题。那是些什么问题我已记不清，只记得是蛮technical的问题。正常情况下，如果问题回答不上，一般人会说“This is a good questions”或者直说“I can’t give you an answer”。可是，张首晟回避不答，硬是扯到其他不相关的东西。可见他心虚，心思的确不在科研。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ocpa9&quot;&gt;OCPA9&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;跟张首晟最后一次见面，是17年7月在清华举办的OCPA9会议。OCPA是由北美华人物理学家发起的全球华人物理学会，每两三年开一次。对于张首晟来说，OCPA有特殊的意义。1992年，成立不久的OCPA决定要办一个奖颁给优秀年轻华人物理学家，而第一个得奖的正是张首晟。当时的张首晟，只有29岁，&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;这个奖在物理学界的知名度似乎不是很高，但其实含金量很高。只要看看颁奖委员会成员和获奖名单就知道：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;颁奖委员会成员名单：杨振宁、李政道、崔琦、朱经武、沈元壤、李雅达（Partrick Lee）、沈呂九等等&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;获奖名单：张首晟、沈志勋、文小刚、杜瑞瑞、叶乃裳、许岑珂、祁晓亮、陈宇林、傅亮、麦建辉（Kin-Fai Mak）等等&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;在OCPA9上，张首晟分享当年获奖的照片，并以此鼓励年轻人努力做科研。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/zhang_shoucheng/ocpa9.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;OCPA9&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;OCPA9会上，他分享当年拿到的OCPA OYRA奖时的照片，鼓励年轻人努力做科研。（言下之意：如果你能拿到这个奖，就说明你跟我一样牛逼^_^）&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;结语&quot;&gt;结语&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;网上流传着这么一个故事：张首晟在柏林自由大学本科毕业以后，对未来感到非常迷茫。去哥廷根造访的时候，他到了一片墓地，那里躺着高斯、希尔伯特、海森堡、波恩等著名数学家和物理学家。每个人的墓碑上没有墓志铭，只有一道公式。这几个墓碑让年轻的张首晟感到非常震撼。人活一辈子到底为了什么？要为这个世界做出什么贡献？留下什么东西？或许一道公式就够了。张首晟走了，可能没有留下一道公式，但他完成了一个拼图：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/zhang_shoucheng/quantum_hall_trio.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Quantum Hall Trio&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Quantum Hall Trio&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">今天在微信上知道张首晟去世的噩耗，非常震惊。两天前我才在专栏里回忆了一下读博士这前两年做了些什么，学了些什么。里面提到我参加过的会议，其中有三个，张首晟都去了。我跟张首晟不熟，他不认识我，我也没跟他说过几句话。我仰慕他，为他做出的物理贡献感到骄傲，但同时我又对他后期分心搞风投感到不满。在这里我想写的是，在这三次会议里张首晟说过的一些东西，一般报道不会提到的一些小事情，以作纪念。</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">博士中期考核</title><link href="https://huangjunye.github.io//2018/12/%E5%8D%9A%E5%A3%AB%E4%B8%AD%E6%9C%9F%E8%80%83%E6%A0%B8.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="博士中期考核" /><published>2018-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://huangjunye.github.io//2018/12/%E5%8D%9A%E5%A3%AB%E4%B8%AD%E6%9C%9F%E8%80%83%E6%A0%B8</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://huangjunye.github.io//2018/12/%E5%8D%9A%E5%A3%AB%E4%B8%AD%E6%9C%9F%E8%80%83%E6%A0%B8.html">&lt;p&gt;很久没在知乎上写东西了。不只是在这个专栏，这两三年甚至连答案都没写过几个。这个专栏有上百个人关注，却一直都没有更新，承蒙大家错爱。上一篇讲的还是我刚拿到博士录取通知的事，现在我都快要博士中期考核了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;正是因为在写中期考核报告，我回顾了一下博士前两年的经历，学到的东西，感觉差强人意，还过得去。虽然还没发表任何论文，但是学到了不少知识。我想在这个专栏里也写个类似于中期考核报告的文章。在这里挖些坑，写下我要写的文章，这样我就不会一直拖着。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;参加会议的经历&quot;&gt;参加会议的经历&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;majonext2017&quot;&gt;Majonext2017&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/qe/majonext2017.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Majonext2017&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Majonext2017大合照&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;尽管还没有论文，我仍然很幸运地在新加坡之外参加了两次学术会议。第一个是17年5月在西班牙马略卡岛举行的Majonext2017会议，另一个是下面会提到的OCPA9。&lt;a href=&quot;http://majonext2017.ifisc.uib-csic.es/&quot;&gt;Majonext2017会议&lt;/a&gt;大概是第一个以马约拉纳费米子为主题的诡异。会上大牛云集，Kouwenhoven、Marcus、Molenkamp、Jarillo-Herrero、张首晟都在。在会上也认识了不少学生辈的大牛，特别是邓明堂和李川。这两个人现在都当上教授了。这是我第一次正式参加的学术会议，而且学到了很多东西，虽然过了那么久当时受到的震撼和感想都忘得差不多了，但是我一定要认真写下来。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ocpa9&quot;&gt;OCPA9&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/qe/ocpa9.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;OCPA9&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;OCPA9大合照&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;如果你有关注这个专栏的话，你大概知道&lt;a href=&quot;https://zhuanlan.zhihu.com/p/19788446&quot;&gt;我的物理征程&lt;/a&gt;起源于在新加坡举行的&lt;a href=&quot;https://livestream.com/NTU/ocpa8&quot;&gt;OCPA8&lt;/a&gt;（第八届全球华人物理学家大会）。三年以后（17年7月）&lt;a href=&quot;http://ocpaweb.org/home/ocpa9-conference/&quot;&gt;OCPA9&lt;/a&gt;在清华举办，虽然我参加完Majonext，但是导师还是非常接近人情地让我去北京参加对我意义重大的OCPA9。（当然，那是因为我帮他申请到了三百万新币的科研经费。）会议组织方面，OCPA9比OCPA8要差太多了。小报告在普通教室里进行，有些报告听的人多，课室里连站的地方都没有。吃饭要走大老远到饭堂吃，吃完又得赶紧往回走，很多老教授走不过来要错过下午第一场报告。不过OCPA会上报告的广度和深度是很多会议都比不上的。虽然我做的是凝聚态，但是我听得最多的是高能。能够从项目主持人口里听到关于环形正负电子对撞机、天琴计划、锦屏暗物质探测实验室的进展，是非常难得的经历。关于OCPA9的文章其实我已经写了两千字了，但是最后没有发表出来。回头修改一下就发表。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;qm90workshop-on-topological-phase-transitions-and-new-developments和feynman100&quot;&gt;QM90、Workshop on Topological Phase Transitions and New Developments和Feynman100&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;南洋理工大学有个&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ntu.edu.sg/ias/Pages/default.aspx&quot;&gt;高等研究院（IAS）&lt;/a&gt;，不怎么做研究，但是常常组织非常高规格的学术会议。这些会议大多是纪念性质的，所以报告的内容不会太枯燥难懂，一般我去都是为了听大牛讲故事。本科的时候我就去过不少。我的Google Drive里有张记录我见过的诺奖得主名单。这几年来参加IAS的各种会议，见过的诺奖得主居然接近50个！！！我的目标是Gotta Catch ‘Em All。O(∩_∩)O~&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/qe/qm90.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;QM90&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;QM90大合照&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2017年是量子力学奠基90周年，IAS搞了一个&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ntu.edu.sg/IAS/Events/2017/QM90/Pages/default.aspx&quot;&gt;纪念量子力学的会议&lt;/a&gt;。单诺奖得主就有六个：David Gross、Anthony Leggett、Gerard ’t Hooft、Arieh Warshel、​Rudy Marcus、杨振宁。像张首晟、薛其坤、叶军、大野英男、Stuart Parkin、Peter Zoller这级别的大牛都只能算是小字辈。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/qe/haldane.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Duncan Haldane&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Duncan Haldane，邓肯·好蛋，江湖人称‘’阿笠博士‘’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2016年，拓扑物理拿了诺贝尔奖。没过几个月，IAS就把Haldane和Kosterlitz请来，搞了一个&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ntu.edu.sg/IAS/Events/2017/TPT17/Pages/default.aspx&quot;&gt;会议&lt;/a&gt;。人称“阿笠博士”的Haldane还把诺奖金牌拿出来任人摸玩，可惜我没摸到T_T。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/qe/feynman100.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Feynman100&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;费曼100周年纪念会大合照&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;今年是费曼诞辰100周年，IAS在10月底搞了一个&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ntu.edu.sg/IAS/Events/2018/RF100/Pages/default.aspx&quot;&gt;纪念费曼的会议&lt;/a&gt;。据会议的组织者私下跟我透露的信息，本来Caltech都没打算纪念费曼，但是IAS执意要搞，所以Caltech也得自己搞一个。一个跟费曼无亲无故的太平洋小岛国要搞隆重的纪念活动，而费曼长期工作的Caltech总不能无动于衷吧？那得多丢人现眼啊？但是规格还是差太远了。Caltech的纪念会议只搞了一晚加一天，IAS的纪念会议搞了整整三天，还在新加坡的艺术科学博物馆搞一个半年的费曼展。这个会议安排的很有意思，一天只有4个人讲，讲60分钟，讨论45分钟。本来我特别担心讨论那么长时间会冷场，没想到那么长的讨论时间都不够用，大家都踊跃发言，互动感特别地强。虽然作报告的只有20个人，但是台下还有很多不做报告的大牛。财大气粗的IAS从美国大老远的把费曼的家人、同事、朋友都请了过来！在讨论的时间里，这些熟悉费曼的人讲了很多关于费曼的故事。这次会议对我的影响也是非常深远。我应该趁热打铁把文章写出来，记录一下。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;这些会议规格都很高但是规模都很小，一般只有一两百人参加，所以这些诺奖得主、大牛不只可以远观，还可以“亵玩“。有什么问题可以随便发问，吃饭、吃茶点的时候还可以去找他们搭话。QM90的时候我跟‘t Hooft讨论了一些真空和黑洞的问题。Feynman100的时候我问了Wilczek好多关于拓扑超导的问题和他对量子计算的看法。但是让我印象最深刻的是Peter Zoller。我问他，现在量子计算机有那么多种硬件实现方式，包括超导、离子阱和最新的拓扑超导，到底哪一种才是“晶体管“？他说，“我以为做量子计算就像登山。尽管你登的这座山未必是最高的珠穆朗玛峰，无论是乞力马扎罗山还是阿尔卑斯山，在登山过程中也都能看到独特的风景。登山的乐趣不在于登顶，而在于欣赏途中的风景。做量子计算也一样，让我们多爬几座山，欣赏不一样的风景。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;理论知识&quot;&gt;理论知识&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;读博士两年了，物理基础知识仍然不是很扎实。在实验室里，基础物理知识最差的是我，研究课题最难的却也是我。我理解得不算很深入，但是我希望能把学到的知识写在这个专栏里。至少可以梳理一下知识，也希望知乎的大牛指点一下。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;我想写的理论知识有：二维超导、拓扑超导、拓扑量子计算、非局域自旋阀、自旋输运、自旋弛豫。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;实验仪器知识&quot;&gt;实验仪器知识&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;做实验物理还学到很多在论文里比较少提到的实验仪器工作原理和使用技巧。上面提到的理论知识只要能看懂英文，就能找到很多相关文献。但是关于实验仪器的文献就比较少了，所以写下来大概更有价值，也更符合我这个专栏的名字。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;我想写的实验仪器知识有：脉管循环制冷机工作原理、稀释制冷机工作原理、低温过滤器种类和工作原理、测量仪器远程控制和软件、锁相放大器、范德华异质结转移技术。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;实验数据分析&quot;&gt;实验数据分析&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;做实验除了做样品和测量，更重要的是数据分析。如果数据不是很庞大，分析不是很复杂，一般来说Origin是够用了。Origin也可以编程，不过LabTalk编程语言非常不友好，指令和函数的名字更像汇编。Origin还可以用一个类似C语言的Origin-C编程。但是尝试过LabTalk以后我决定放弃用Origin做数据分析。但是还在测量的时候一边测一边快速画图还是没有什么软件能比得上Origin。后期数据分析我用Matlab和Jupyter Notebook。这一部分我想写一篇文章详细讲一讲。虽然我懂的不多，免不了献丑，但是希望能够抛砖引玉，得到大牛的指点。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;我还想写一些具体的例子。我发现一些非常浅显的数据分析，在没有前人指导的情况下，很难自学。真是因为都太简单了，论文里一般都是一笔带过，而我看完以后都是一脸懵逼，完全不知道如何下手。比如说：&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/0375960168906233&quot;&gt;Aslamazov-Larkin formula&lt;/a&gt;长什么样子？很多文章都说超导转变温度可以用这个公式来拟合，然后引用原文。而原文是50年前写出来的，讨论了两个形式，而且我也不清楚50年过去这个公式是不是有个更好的形式，或者更精准的常数等等。这么简单的一个公式我也花了好几天才搞清楚。类似的情况有&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;如何从Hc-T数据中算出金兹堡-朗道相干长度&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;如何用&lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.aps.org/prl/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevLett.41.121&quot;&gt;Halperin-Nelson公式&lt;/a&gt;拟合得到BKT相变温度&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;为什么BKT相变温度可以在VI测量里得到？为什么BKT相变发生在 [公式] ?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;如何用三维金兹堡-朗道模型和二维Tinkham模型拟合Hc2的各向异性&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;如何用&lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.aps.org/prb/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevB.25.4515&quot;&gt;BTK模型&lt;/a&gt;拟合隧道谱&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;坑挖了那么多，感觉一年也写不完。暂且把目标定为博士毕业前写完吧！&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">很久没在知乎上写东西了。不只是在这个专栏，这两三年甚至连答案都没写过几个。这个专栏有上百个人关注，却一直都没有更新，承蒙大家错爱。上一篇讲的还是我刚拿到博士录取通知的事，现在我都快要博士中期考核了。</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Feynman Lecture Vol. I Chap. 2: Basic Physics</title><link href="https://huangjunye.github.io//2018/11/17/feynman-lecture-vol-i-chap-2-basic-physics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Feynman Lecture Vol. I Chap. 2: Basic Physics" /><published>2018-11-17T07:11:55+00:00</published><updated>2018-11-17T07:11:55+00:00</updated><id>https://huangjunye.github.io//2018/11/17/feynman-lecture-vol-i-chap-2-basic-physics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://huangjunye.github.io//2018/11/17/feynman-lecture-vol-i-chap-2-basic-physics/">&lt;p&gt;It is incredible how weak my perseverance is. Just one week after my resolution to read and write about Feynman Lecture, I procrastinated. This summary was due one week ago! I did continue to read the book, even faster than I planned; I am in chapter 6 already. However, I stopped thinking again. Reading faster or more is not the point of this exercise. What I want to change is the habit of thinking. I should stop reading and thinking about what I have read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary of Chapter 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This chapter is about the most fundamental ideas about physics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, Feynman discussed about the scientific method. The scientific method is about observation, reason and experiment. We see something about the world; we think about why these things happen and formulate an idea; we then do experiments to check out the ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To check the rules of nature, to verify our understandings of the nature, there are three ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Examine the rules directly under controlled environment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Examine the prediction or consequence of rules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand by rough approximation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not so sure whether I understand what Feynman said, especially the third way. For a better understanding, I should analyse a concrete example. For example, gravitational law says that the gravitational force between objects scales linearly with their masses and inversely to the square of distance between them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first way, we can imagine doing an experiment to measure the gravitational force between two heavy objects, such as two balls. The gravitational force can be measured by a torsion balance. (See &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cavendish_experiment&quot;&gt;Cavendish experiment&lt;/a&gt;) I could change the small ball to change its balance distance between the small and big ball. In a series of experiment, I can find out the force dependence of the masses of the balls as well as the distance. This would be a direct proof of the gravitational law. Of course, this experiment is no easy task. The force measured is extremely small. To prevent air current and temperature changes from interfering the measurement, Cavendish place the entire apparatus in a wooden box. And he observed the torsion balance far away using a telescope to prevent his own mass from interfering the result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the second way, we can examine the consequences or prediction of gravitational law. This brings the story of the discovery of Neptune. Astronomers predicted the existence of  Neptune base on motions of Uranus that could not be accounted for by the actions of the other planets according to Newton's law of gravity. Neptune was later discovered pointing a telescope to the position calculated carefully using Newton's law of gravity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the third way, I don't know how to do it using the gravitational law example. But perhaps I can use dark matter or dark energy. I think right now we are understanding dark matter by approximation. We don't yet know what it is but we do know it exists, we know how much there is and we more or less know that it doesn't interact with other matter easily. From here and there we are gathering pieces of puzzles, until one day a breakthrough come about and we will understand it better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feynman then talked about unification of different phenomena. Heat, electricity, mechanics, magnetism, etc. were all considered different and unrelated. But later we understood, heat and mechanics are strongly related. Heat is just movement of atoms. Electricity and magnetism is two sides of the same coin: electromagnetism. Light is also related to electricity and magnetism; it is electromagnetic wave. This eventually brings the question: is there a theory of everything? I asked a related question to Frank Wilczek after his talk &quot;There is plenty more room at the bottom&quot; in Feynman 100 conference: &quot;Is there a bottom?&quot; Frank Wilczek answered that he doesn't know whether there will be a bottom or a theory of everything, but he think there will be a final theory. A final theory refers to a theory that not necessarily explains everything but most of the things in great enough details that we are satisfied with it. I personally don't believe in final theory. We learn from the history of modern physics that we can't settle for satisfaction. At the end of 19th century, the triumph of Maxwell's electromagnetism made people think that we understood everything. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/nphys921&quot;&gt;&quot;In this field, almost everything is already discovered, and all that remains is to fill a few holes.&quot;&lt;/a&gt; Max Plank was so told by his supervisor Phillip von Jolly. What an irony to say that to the man who became the father of quantum mechanics later!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feynman continues by describing our understanding of physics before 1920. More precisely, it should be physics before special and general relativity and quantum mechanics because both relativity theories were already discovered before 1920. At that time, we understood the universe is in a three-dimensional space of geometry. We knew there are particles such as atoms and electrons. We understood there are forces between objects, such as gravitational force and electromagnetic force. We understood that electricity and magnetism is strongly related and light is just a small portion of the entire spectrum of electromagnetic waves. We understood gas as a movement of particles and heat as the random internal motions. We understood there were different kinds of elements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The description of quantum physics follows physics before 1920. The core ideas of quantum physics were introduced: uncertainty principle, particle-wave duality, probability nature. Feynman continues the story with his own field of expertise: quantum electrodynamics, aka QED and its prediction of anti-particles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last part was dedicated to the most recent particle experiments at time of the lecture around 1960. Strong and weak interaction was not well understood. Quarks were not known. Standard model of particle physics will need another decade to develop. It is for this part that I realise how fast physics has developed. We know so much more about all the particles and how they interact. We even found Higgs boson which gives mass to all other particles. We have a much better understand of how the universe was born. Although Feynman didn't mention much about condensed matter physics, but I could read elsewhere to know about the understanding of CMP in 1960s. Transistor was just invented. BCS theory was newly minted and we thought we understood superconductivity completely. There was no quantum Hall effect and the fractional and spin Hall effects. No high Tc superconductors. No topological materials. No cold atoms. No graphene and 2D materials. No perovskites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Questions for Chapter 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn't spend much thinking about any problems deeply this last two weeks. I should really change this habit. For now, I will write the questions I have for chapter 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do things get charged by rubbing? What determines which thing gets positive and which gets negative? Presumably this has to do with the ability of certain material to hold/attract electrons. But I would like to understand deeper. As least I should be able to explain why rubber rub against silk produces different charge from glass rub against silk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why is a AC current equivalent to electromagnetic wave? An AC current is driven by an alternating electric field. Is that equivalent to EM wave because the AC electric field will generate AC magnetic field?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the theoretical basis for uncertainty principle? Is it an axiom of quantum mechanics?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anti-particle puzzle. Where is there more particle than anti-particles? Does it mean that there were more particles than anti-particles since the beginning of the universe? That means the universe was not born from nothing. Alternatively, maybe there is a way to get rid of anti-particles. But in that case, the conservation of particles will be violated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the definition of anti-particle? I thought anti-particle is the same as particle except the charge is the opposite. If that is right, any particle without charges will be its own anti-particles. Perhaps this is only a necessary but not sufficient condition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can we always ask nature about &quot; what is the use for it&quot;? Is there always a reason for something to be?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the speed of light in media? Can we slow down light?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are dark matter and dark energy? What is the distinction between the two? How do we know how much percentage they occupy in the universe?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;hjunye&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;h.jun.ye@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Huang Junye&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>h.jun.ye@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">It is incredible how weak my perseverance is. Just one week after my resolution to read and write about Feynman Lecture, I procrastinated. This summary was due one week ago! I did continue to read the book, even faster than I planned; I am in chapter 6 already. However, I stopped thinking again. Reading faster or more is not the point of this exercise. What I want to change is the habit of thinking. I should stop reading and thinking about what I have read. Summary of Chapter 2 This chapter is about the most fundamental ideas about physics. First, Feynman discussed about the scientific method. The scientific method is about observation, reason and experiment. We see something about the world; we think about why these things happen and formulate an idea; we then do experiments to check out the ideas. To check the rules of nature, to verify our understandings of the nature, there are three ways: Examine the rules directly under controlled environment Examine the prediction or consequence of rules Understand by rough approximation I am not so sure whether I understand what Feynman said, especially the third way. For a better understanding, I should analyse a concrete example. For example, gravitational law says that the gravitational force between objects scales linearly with their masses and inversely to the square of distance between them. In the first way, we can imagine doing an experiment to measure the gravitational force between two heavy objects, such as two balls. The gravitational force can be measured by a torsion balance. (See Cavendish experiment) I could change the small ball to change its balance distance between the small and big ball. In a series of experiment, I can find out the force dependence of the masses of the balls as well as the distance. This would be a direct proof of the gravitational law. Of course, this experiment is no easy task. The force measured is extremely small. To prevent air current and temperature changes from interfering the measurement, Cavendish place the entire apparatus in a wooden box. And he observed the torsion balance far away using a telescope to prevent his own mass from interfering the result. In the second way, we can examine the consequences or prediction of gravitational law. This brings the story of the discovery of Neptune. Astronomers predicted the existence of  Neptune base on motions of Uranus that could not be accounted for by the actions of the other planets according to Newton's law of gravity. Neptune was later discovered pointing a telescope to the position calculated carefully using Newton's law of gravity. In the third way, I don't know how to do it using the gravitational law example. But perhaps I can use dark matter or dark energy. I think right now we are understanding dark matter by approximation. We don't yet know what it is but we do know it exists, we know how much there is and we more or less know that it doesn't interact with other matter easily. From here and there we are gathering pieces of puzzles, until one day a breakthrough come about and we will understand it better. Feynman then talked about unification of different phenomena. Heat, electricity, mechanics, magnetism, etc. were all considered different and unrelated. But later we understood, heat and mechanics are strongly related. Heat is just movement of atoms. Electricity and magnetism is two sides of the same coin: electromagnetism. Light is also related to electricity and magnetism; it is electromagnetic wave. This eventually brings the question: is there a theory of everything? I asked a related question to Frank Wilczek after his talk &quot;There is plenty more room at the bottom&quot; in Feynman 100 conference: &quot;Is there a bottom?&quot; Frank Wilczek answered that he doesn't know whether there will be a bottom or a theory of everything, but he think there will be a final theory. A final theory refers to a theory that not necessarily explains everything but most of the things in great enough details that we are satisfied with it. I personally don't believe in final theory. We learn from the history of modern physics that we can't settle for satisfaction. At the end of 19th century, the triumph of Maxwell's electromagnetism made people think that we understood everything. &quot;In this field, almost everything is already discovered, and all that remains is to fill a few holes.&quot; Max Plank was so told by his supervisor Phillip von Jolly. What an irony to say that to the man who became the father of quantum mechanics later! Feynman continues by describing our understanding of physics before 1920. More precisely, it should be physics before special and general relativity and quantum mechanics because both relativity theories were already discovered before 1920. At that time, we understood the universe is in a three-dimensional space of geometry. We knew there are particles such as atoms and electrons. We understood there are forces between objects, such as gravitational force and electromagnetic force. We understood that electricity and magnetism is strongly related and light is just a small portion of the entire spectrum of electromagnetic waves. We understood gas as a movement of particles and heat as the random internal motions. We understood there were different kinds of elements. The description of quantum physics follows physics before 1920. The core ideas of quantum physics were introduced: uncertainty principle, particle-wave duality, probability nature. Feynman continues the story with his own field of expertise: quantum electrodynamics, aka QED and its prediction of anti-particles. The last part was dedicated to the most recent particle experiments at time of the lecture around 1960. Strong and weak interaction was not well understood. Quarks were not known. Standard model of particle physics will need another decade to develop. It is for this part that I realise how fast physics has developed. We know so much more about all the particles and how they interact. We even found Higgs boson which gives mass to all other particles. We have a much better understand of how the universe was born. Although Feynman didn't mention much about condensed matter physics, but I could read elsewhere to know about the understanding of CMP in 1960s. Transistor was just invented. BCS theory was newly minted and we thought we understood superconductivity completely. There was no quantum Hall effect and the fractional and spin Hall effects. No high Tc superconductors. No topological materials. No cold atoms. No graphene and 2D materials. No perovskites. Questions for Chapter 2 I didn't spend much thinking about any problems deeply this last two weeks. I should really change this habit. For now, I will write the questions I have for chapter 2. How do things get charged by rubbing? What determines which thing gets positive and which gets negative? Presumably this has to do with the ability of certain material to hold/attract electrons. But I would like to understand deeper. As least I should be able to explain why rubber rub against silk produces different charge from glass rub against silk. Why is a AC current equivalent to electromagnetic wave? An AC current is driven by an alternating electric field. Is that equivalent to EM wave because the AC electric field will generate AC magnetic field? What is the theoretical basis for uncertainty principle? Is it an axiom of quantum mechanics? Anti-particle puzzle. Where is there more particle than anti-particles? Does it mean that there were more particles than anti-particles since the beginning of the universe? That means the universe was not born from nothing. Alternatively, maybe there is a way to get rid of anti-particles. But in that case, the conservation of particles will be violated. What is the definition of anti-particle? I thought anti-particle is the same as particle except the charge is the opposite. If that is right, any particle without charges will be its own anti-particles. Perhaps this is only a necessary but not sufficient condition. Can we always ask nature about &quot; what is the use for it&quot;? Is there always a reason for something to be? What is the speed of light in media? Can we slow down light? What are dark matter and dark energy? What is the distinction between the two? How do we know how much percentage they occupy in the universe?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Feynman Lectures Vol. I Chap. 1: Atoms in Motion</title><link href="https://huangjunye.github.io//2018/11/06/feynman-lectures-vol-i-chap-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Feynman Lectures Vol. I Chap. 1: Atoms in Motion" /><published>2018-11-06T03:34:03+00:00</published><updated>2018-11-06T03:34:03+00:00</updated><id>https://huangjunye.github.io//2018/11/06/feynman-lectures-vol-i-chap-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://huangjunye.github.io//2018/11/06/feynman-lectures-vol-i-chap-1/">&lt;p&gt;After attending Feynman 100 conference last week, I decided that I should start learning physics again from scratch. At first, I thought it would be a good idea to start from solid state physics. Because it is not too difficult for me, and it is relatively close to my experiments so that I can benefits from learning in a short time and that in turn can keep me motivated to learn. In addition, if I find some gaps in my understanding, I can easily read some chapters on fundamental theories (quantum mechanics, statistical mechanics, or electrodynamics, etc.) without digging too deep or spending too much time on them. On the other hand, learning solid state physics can also help me understanding more advanced concepts that are directly related to my experiments, such as superconductivity and spintronics. However, after reading a few pages of Feynman lectures, I knew that this is &lt;em&gt;the book&lt;/em&gt; to start. I realised what I wanted to learn from physics is not only the physics knowledge itself, but also the physicist's way of thinking, or first-principle reasoning. For that, there is no better book than Feynman lectures. Just like what I learned from attending Feynman 100 conference (by the way, I still owe my readers an article about the conference, if anyone reads my blog, at all :P) and Youtube videos about Feynman, Feynman is a great teacher. He used the simplest words to explain physics. He really hated jargons. Reading Feynman lectures is a pure joy, because I feel I can think like Feynman, I feel smart! I spent about an hour everyday last week in the morning reading Feynman lectures. It was an enjoyable intellectual treat that I haven't had for a really long time. First time after a long while, probably after high school, I felt I could think clearly about some problems and started to question. This is a good start to train my first-principle reasoning. I didn't feel lazy to read the lectures; I actually looked forward to read them. Let's hope this will continue for a while, at least until Christmas? Let's don't be too ambitious. Do it step by step. My next goal to see my next summary/progress post next weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Progress Report Structure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because this is the first post of the series, I am going to say a few words about the structure of the progress report I have in mind. First, I will write a brief summary of the chapter. Then I will expand on a few concepts or problems that I found interesting depends on the time I have to think about the problems and/or the time I have to write about them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary of Chapter 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first chapter, Feynman discussed about his idea about teaching physics, which also reflects his view on physics in general. He discussed why we can't teach physics from basic axioms, why we need to first learn the simpler, &quot;wrong&quot; theory, before learning the more advanced, &quot;right&quot; theory. First, this is the history of physics. We first figured out classical theories to explain our everyday objects and then we figured out strange theories to explain puzzling experimental facts as our knowledge grew and the experimental techniques improved. We don't have the &quot;correct&quot; theory. It is important for students to realise that all theories are only approximations of the &quot;truth&quot;. Therefore, it is a good idea to teach classical theories before teaching quantum theories. Another reason is that classical theories are easier to understand because we can understand them from our everyday experience. From there, we can build up our intuition and also our confidence in mathematic description of phenomena so that later on we can have some ground to rely on when things get very strange. In the second part, Feynman outlined our over-all picture of the world. In his opinion, the single most important concept in physics, or even in the entire field of science, is the atomic hypothesis that everything is made of atoms. He used water as an example to illustrate the power of the atomic hypothesis. He explained the different of atomic arrangement of the three phases of water: water, ice and vapour. We can easily understand why water expands in volume when it freezes to become ice: because ice has a hollow structure with a lot of empty space between the atoms. We can also understand why blowing a hot soup can cool it: we blow to move the water vapour on top of the soup so that it will keep evaporating and the evaporating vapour removes heat from the soup. Feynman carried on to explain dissolution and chemical reactions from atomic point of view. This chapter was wonderful. It stimulated me to think about many basic questions in science:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why do some substances dissolve less as the temperature increases? (retrograde solubility)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why does burning happen? Why do we need ignition to start a fire and how does burning continues after ignition? How are fire (plasma) and light generated from burning?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does nose sense smell?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why does Brownian motion happen?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is everything physical? How can we understand things like consciousness from a physical point of view?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to calculate the resolution limit of microscopes? How to calculate the diffraction limit and beat the diffraction limit?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week I only have time to dig into the first problem, retrograde solubility. I was particularly interested in this problem because I tried to understand it in high school when I was very good in chemistry and when I was still feeling powerful enough to understand the world by thinking by myself. I thought it would be rewarding to solve a little mystery that puzzled my arrogant young self.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Retrograde solubility&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, why do some substances dissolve less as the temperature increases? If you search on the internet, you will find an answer based on Le Chatelier principle. Le Chatelier principle tells you that, in a chemical equilibrium, when some changes happen, the system will adjust itself to reverse the change and reach a new equilibrium. Retrograde solubility is found in substances that produce heat when they dissolve, that is, the dissolution process is exothermal. So when the temperature increases, the solubility is reduced because the system want to reduce the heat of the system so as to resist the increase of temperature according to Le Chatelier principle. This is all very intuitive and satisfying but somehow I am not very happy about Le Chatelier principle. It's like Lenz law, Pauli exclusion principle or Hund's rule. These rules all sound like some words came up by some famous scientists. I won't believe them unless you give me proves! So I tried to understand the problem using elementary thermodynamics that I remember. An exothermal dissolution process means the enthalpy of dissolution is negative. (ΔH&amp;lt;0) The fact that the substances can dissolve means dissolution lower the overall energy of the system, that is Gibbs free energy change is negative (ΔG &amp;lt;0)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;$latex \Delta G = \Delta H - T \Delta S $&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If ΔS is positive, ΔG become more negative when temperature increases, which means dissolution is more preferred so the solubility increases. Otherwise, if ΔS is negative, the solubility decreases. Put it more formally. In a simple dissolution chemical reaction&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;$latex AB=A^{+} + B^{-}$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;$latex \Delta G = -RT ln K $ where $latex K=[A^+][B^-]$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;$latex \partial (\Delta G) / \partial T = -R ln K = - \Delta S $&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;&gt;When ΔS &amp;lt; 0, ΔG increases with temperature, K decreases and so do the concentration of A+ and B-. If ΔH &amp;gt; 0, that is the dissolution absorbs heat, then ΔG is positive when ΔS is negative, in which case dissolution won't happen. Therefore, retrograde solubility only happens when dissolution produces heat. But exothermal dissolution is a necessary condition, not a sufficient condition. For retrograde solubility to happen, we need ΔH &amp;lt; 0 &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; ΔS &amp;lt; 0. How is it possible that the entropy reduces after dissolution? Entropy is a measure of disorder. A reduction of entropy after dissolution suggests that A+ and B- forms a more ordered structure with the solvent than in the solute A-B form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this part, I haven't found a definite answer. But it seems many sulphates ($latex SO_{4}^{2-}$) and selenates ($latex SeO_{4}^{2-}$) have retrograde solubilities. Sulphur and selenium lie in the same column of the periodic table, so it is understandable that sulphates and selenates have similar properties. I guess somehow $latex SO_{4}^{2-}$ and $latex SeO_{4}^{2-}$ can form large complexes with water molecules. The bonds have large energy combining with high coordination number produce more energy than the energy needed to break $latex SO_{4}^{2-}$ with the cations. And the large $latex H_2 O$ complexes somehow have more organised structure than in the sulphates which reduces the entropy as well. To get a more concrete answer, I will need to dig deeper in the literature. For now, I will stop the analysis here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an incomplete list of salts with retrograde solubility according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solubility_table&quot;&gt;solubility table on Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$latex Ca(CH_3 COOH)_2, CaCrO_4, Ca(OH)_2, CaSeO_4, CaSO_4, Ce_2(SeO_4)_3$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$latex Co(IO_3)_2 \cdot 2H_2 O, Er_2 (SO_4)_3 \cdot 8 H_2 O, Gd_2 (SO_4)_3, Ho_2 (SO_4)_3 \cdot 8H_2O, La_2 (SO_4)_3$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$latex  LI_2 CO_3, Li_2SeO_3, Li_2 C_4 H_4 O_6, MnSO_4, Nd_2 (SeO_4)_3, Pr_2 (SO_4)_3, Yb_2 (SO_4)_3, Y_2 (SO_4)_3 $&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;hjunye&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;h.jun.ye@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Huang Junye&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>h.jun.ye@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">After attending Feynman 100 conference last week, I decided that I should start learning physics again from scratch. At first, I thought it would be a good idea to start from solid state physics. Because it is not too difficult for me, and it is relatively close to my experiments so that I can benefits from learning in a short time and that in turn can keep me motivated to learn. In addition, if I find some gaps in my understanding, I can easily read some chapters on fundamental theories (quantum mechanics, statistical mechanics, or electrodynamics, etc.) without digging too deep or spending too much time on them. On the other hand, learning solid state physics can also help me understanding more advanced concepts that are directly related to my experiments, such as superconductivity and spintronics. However, after reading a few pages of Feynman lectures, I knew that this is the book to start. I realised what I wanted to learn from physics is not only the physics knowledge itself, but also the physicist's way of thinking, or first-principle reasoning. For that, there is no better book than Feynman lectures. Just like what I learned from attending Feynman 100 conference (by the way, I still owe my readers an article about the conference, if anyone reads my blog, at all :P) and Youtube videos about Feynman, Feynman is a great teacher. He used the simplest words to explain physics. He really hated jargons. Reading Feynman lectures is a pure joy, because I feel I can think like Feynman, I feel smart! I spent about an hour everyday last week in the morning reading Feynman lectures. It was an enjoyable intellectual treat that I haven't had for a really long time. First time after a long while, probably after high school, I felt I could think clearly about some problems and started to question. This is a good start to train my first-principle reasoning. I didn't feel lazy to read the lectures; I actually looked forward to read them. Let's hope this will continue for a while, at least until Christmas? Let's don't be too ambitious. Do it step by step. My next goal to see my next summary/progress post next weekend. Progress Report Structure Because this is the first post of the series, I am going to say a few words about the structure of the progress report I have in mind. First, I will write a brief summary of the chapter. Then I will expand on a few concepts or problems that I found interesting depends on the time I have to think about the problems and/or the time I have to write about them. Summary of Chapter 1 In the first chapter, Feynman discussed about his idea about teaching physics, which also reflects his view on physics in general. He discussed why we can't teach physics from basic axioms, why we need to first learn the simpler, &quot;wrong&quot; theory, before learning the more advanced, &quot;right&quot; theory. First, this is the history of physics. We first figured out classical theories to explain our everyday objects and then we figured out strange theories to explain puzzling experimental facts as our knowledge grew and the experimental techniques improved. We don't have the &quot;correct&quot; theory. It is important for students to realise that all theories are only approximations of the &quot;truth&quot;. Therefore, it is a good idea to teach classical theories before teaching quantum theories. Another reason is that classical theories are easier to understand because we can understand them from our everyday experience. From there, we can build up our intuition and also our confidence in mathematic description of phenomena so that later on we can have some ground to rely on when things get very strange. In the second part, Feynman outlined our over-all picture of the world. In his opinion, the single most important concept in physics, or even in the entire field of science, is the atomic hypothesis that everything is made of atoms. He used water as an example to illustrate the power of the atomic hypothesis. He explained the different of atomic arrangement of the three phases of water: water, ice and vapour. We can easily understand why water expands in volume when it freezes to become ice: because ice has a hollow structure with a lot of empty space between the atoms. We can also understand why blowing a hot soup can cool it: we blow to move the water vapour on top of the soup so that it will keep evaporating and the evaporating vapour removes heat from the soup. Feynman carried on to explain dissolution and chemical reactions from atomic point of view. This chapter was wonderful. It stimulated me to think about many basic questions in science: Why do some substances dissolve less as the temperature increases? (retrograde solubility) Why does burning happen? Why do we need ignition to start a fire and how does burning continues after ignition? How are fire (plasma) and light generated from burning? How does nose sense smell? Why does Brownian motion happen? Is everything physical? How can we understand things like consciousness from a physical point of view? How to calculate the resolution limit of microscopes? How to calculate the diffraction limit and beat the diffraction limit? This week I only have time to dig into the first problem, retrograde solubility. I was particularly interested in this problem because I tried to understand it in high school when I was very good in chemistry and when I was still feeling powerful enough to understand the world by thinking by myself. I thought it would be rewarding to solve a little mystery that puzzled my arrogant young self. Retrograde solubility So, why do some substances dissolve less as the temperature increases? If you search on the internet, you will find an answer based on Le Chatelier principle. Le Chatelier principle tells you that, in a chemical equilibrium, when some changes happen, the system will adjust itself to reverse the change and reach a new equilibrium. Retrograde solubility is found in substances that produce heat when they dissolve, that is, the dissolution process is exothermal. So when the temperature increases, the solubility is reduced because the system want to reduce the heat of the system so as to resist the increase of temperature according to Le Chatelier principle. This is all very intuitive and satisfying but somehow I am not very happy about Le Chatelier principle. It's like Lenz law, Pauli exclusion principle or Hund's rule. These rules all sound like some words came up by some famous scientists. I won't believe them unless you give me proves! So I tried to understand the problem using elementary thermodynamics that I remember. An exothermal dissolution process means the enthalpy of dissolution is negative. (ΔH&amp;lt;0) The fact that the substances can dissolve means dissolution lower the overall energy of the system, that is Gibbs free energy change is negative (ΔG &amp;lt;0) $latex \Delta G = \Delta H - T \Delta S $ If ΔS is positive, ΔG become more negative when temperature increases, which means dissolution is more preferred so the solubility increases. Otherwise, if ΔS is negative, the solubility decreases. Put it more formally. In a simple dissolution chemical reaction $latex AB=A^{+} + B^{-}$ $latex \Delta G = -RT ln K $ where $latex K=[A^+][B^-]$ $latex \partial (\Delta G) / \partial T = -R ln K = - \Delta S $ When ΔS &amp;lt; 0, ΔG increases with temperature, K decreases and so do the concentration of A+ and B-. If ΔH &amp;gt; 0, that is the dissolution absorbs heat, then ΔG is positive when ΔS is negative, in which case dissolution won't happen. Therefore, retrograde solubility only happens when dissolution produces heat. But exothermal dissolution is a necessary condition, not a sufficient condition. For retrograde solubility to happen, we need ΔH &amp;lt; 0 and ΔS &amp;lt; 0. How is it possible that the entropy reduces after dissolution? Entropy is a measure of disorder. A reduction of entropy after dissolution suggests that A+ and B- forms a more ordered structure with the solvent than in the solute A-B form. For this part, I haven't found a definite answer. But it seems many sulphates ($latex SO_{4}^{2-}$) and selenates ($latex SeO_{4}^{2-}$) have retrograde solubilities. Sulphur and selenium lie in the same column of the periodic table, so it is understandable that sulphates and selenates have similar properties. I guess somehow $latex SO_{4}^{2-}$ and $latex SeO_{4}^{2-}$ can form large complexes with water molecules. The bonds have large energy combining with high coordination number produce more energy than the energy needed to break $latex SO_{4}^{2-}$ with the cations. And the large $latex H_2 O$ complexes somehow have more organised structure than in the sulphates which reduces the entropy as well. To get a more concrete answer, I will need to dig deeper in the literature. For now, I will stop the analysis here. Here is an incomplete list of salts with retrograde solubility according to solubility table on Wikipedia. $latex Ca(CH_3 COOH)_2, CaCrO_4, Ca(OH)_2, CaSeO_4, CaSO_4, Ce_2(SeO_4)_3$ $latex Co(IO_3)_2 \cdot 2H_2 O, Er_2 (SO_4)_3 \cdot 8 H_2 O, Gd_2 (SO_4)_3, Ho_2 (SO_4)_3 \cdot 8H_2O, La_2 (SO_4)_3$ $latex  LI_2 CO_3, Li_2SeO_3, Li_2 C_4 H_4 O_6, MnSO_4, Nd_2 (SeO_4)_3, Pr_2 (SO_4)_3, Yb_2 (SO_4)_3, Y_2 (SO_4)_3 $</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">从零开始学物理</title><link href="https://huangjunye.github.io//2018/10/25/%E4%BB%8E%E9%9B%B6%E5%BC%80%E5%A7%8B%E5%AD%A6%E7%89%A9%E7%90%86/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="从零开始学物理" /><published>2018-10-24T17:51:50+00:00</published><updated>2018-10-24T17:51:50+00:00</updated><id>https://huangjunye.github.io//2018/10/25/%E4%BB%8E%E9%9B%B6%E5%BC%80%E5%A7%8B%E5%AD%A6%E7%89%A9%E7%90%86</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://huangjunye.github.io//2018/10/25/%E4%BB%8E%E9%9B%B6%E5%BC%80%E5%A7%8B%E5%AD%A6%E7%89%A9%E7%90%86/">&lt;p&gt;博士读了快一半了，物理基础还是跟原来一样糟糕。再不努力打好基础，限制以后做研究的深度。其实之前就想过好几次要恶补物理，然而尝试了好几次都半途而废。我决定从今天开始要在博客里记录学物理的过程，作为一种自我监督的方法。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;当然，真的要从零开始学物理，那就得回到经典力学，这样在很长一段时间内都不能感受到打基础对实际研究的帮助。所以我觉得应该从比较接近实验的固态物理开始入手，然后往基础的方向走补量子力学、统计力学和电动力学，同时也可以往更接近研究课题的超导理论。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-221&quot; src=&quot;/assets/learn-physics.png&quot; alt=&quot;Learn physics&quot; width=&quot;1414&quot; height=&quot;202&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;选书&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;固态物理：Ashcroft &amp;amp; Mermin, Solid State Physics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;超导理论：Tinkham, Introduction to Superconductivity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;量子力学：Griffiths, Introduction to Quantum Mechanics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;电动力学：Griffiths, Introduction to Electrodynamics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;统计力学：Schroeder, An Introduction to Thermal Physics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;执行计划&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;先从A&amp;amp;M固态物理入手，慢慢入门。一开始简单的，看过的，一两个星期看完，把题目做完，认真理解，不懂的要认真专研，不要随便跳过。一旦跳过就回到原来不求甚解的习惯。计划一年内看完A&amp;amp;M固态物理。时间慢不要紧，关键是要完全搞懂。即使我一年内把上面所有书看完也没有任何意义，如果我没有认真思考的话。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;每周把学习的记录，思考的问题，写到博客里，以作记录和自我监督。&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;hjunye&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;h.jun.ye@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Huang Junye&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>h.jun.ye@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">博士读了快一半了，物理基础还是跟原来一样糟糕。再不努力打好基础，限制以后做研究的深度。其实之前就想过好几次要恶补物理，然而尝试了好几次都半途而废。我决定从今天开始要在博客里记录学物理的过程，作为一种自我监督的方法。 当然，真的要从零开始学物理，那就得回到经典力学，这样在很长一段时间内都不能感受到打基础对实际研究的帮助。所以我觉得应该从比较接近实验的固态物理开始入手，然后往基础的方向走补量子力学、统计力学和电动力学，同时也可以往更接近研究课题的超导理论。 选书 固态物理：Ashcroft &amp;amp; Mermin, Solid State Physics 超导理论：Tinkham, Introduction to Superconductivity 量子力学：Griffiths, Introduction to Quantum Mechanics 电动力学：Griffiths, Introduction to Electrodynamics 统计力学：Schroeder, An Introduction to Thermal Physics 执行计划 先从A&amp;amp;M固态物理入手，慢慢入门。一开始简单的，看过的，一两个星期看完，把题目做完，认真理解，不懂的要认真专研，不要随便跳过。一旦跳过就回到原来不求甚解的习惯。计划一年内看完A&amp;amp;M固态物理。时间慢不要紧，关键是要完全搞懂。即使我一年内把上面所有书看完也没有任何意义，如果我没有认真思考的话。 每周把学习的记录，思考的问题，写到博客里，以作记录和自我监督。</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">对学术界重新充满希望</title><link href="https://huangjunye.github.io//2018/03/02/%E5%AF%B9%E5%AD%A6%E6%9C%AF%E7%95%8C%E9%87%8D%E6%96%B0%E5%85%85%E6%BB%A1%E5%B8%8C%E6%9C%9B/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="对学术界重新充满希望" /><published>2018-03-01T17:27:24+00:00</published><updated>2018-03-01T17:27:24+00:00</updated><id>https://huangjunye.github.io//2018/03/02/%E5%AF%B9%E5%AD%A6%E6%9C%AF%E7%95%8C%E9%87%8D%E6%96%B0%E5%85%85%E6%BB%A1%E5%B8%8C%E6%9C%9B</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://huangjunye.github.io//2018/03/02/%E5%AF%B9%E5%AD%A6%E6%9C%AF%E7%95%8C%E9%87%8D%E6%96%B0%E5%85%85%E6%BB%A1%E5%B8%8C%E6%9C%9B/">&lt;p&gt;这几天在实验上遇到了一些问题，得到了三个人的无私帮助。这三个人中，一个是我们组之前的博士后，一个是我去年开会的时候认识的，还有一个人我完全不认识，我只读过他的博士论文。以前的博士后帮个忙，感觉天经地义。有一面之缘的朋友帮个忙，感觉也合情合理。但是最后一个人，我们素未谋面，没有丝毫关系。我只读过他的博士论文，发邮件问他一些实验细节。早上八九点的时候给他发邮件，本来还不期待他会回复，没想到过了两个小时便收到详细的答复。而我却花了一整天，到了晚上才回复他，而且还再问了几个问题。半小时后又收到他的回复。他说那天有点忙，第二天再回我。还问我今年去不去APS，去的话可以当面讨论一下。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;从本科开始做科研以来，我只看到一些负面的东西，教授压迫学生、数据分析不严谨造假、教授之间勾心斗角等等，让我对学术界的印象越来越坏。这次得到众人的无私帮助，心里感到非常温暖，对学术界又重新充满希望。&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;hjunye&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;h.jun.ye@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Huang Junye&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>h.jun.ye@gmail.com</email></author><category term="科研" /><summary type="html">这几天在实验上遇到了一些问题，得到了三个人的无私帮助。这三个人中，一个是我们组之前的博士后，一个是我去年开会的时候认识的，还有一个人我完全不认识，我只读过他的博士论文。以前的博士后帮个忙，感觉天经地义。有一面之缘的朋友帮个忙，感觉也合情合理。但是最后一个人，我们素未谋面，没有丝毫关系。我只读过他的博士论文，发邮件问他一些实验细节。早上八九点的时候给他发邮件，本来还不期待他会回复，没想到过了两个小时便收到详细的答复。而我却花了一整天，到了晚上才回复他，而且还再问了几个问题。半小时后又收到他的回复。他说那天有点忙，第二天再回我。还问我今年去不去APS，去的话可以当面讨论一下。 从本科开始做科研以来，我只看到一些负面的东西，教授压迫学生、数据分析不严谨造假、教授之间勾心斗角等等，让我对学术界的印象越来越坏。这次得到众人的无私帮助，心里感到非常温暖，对学术界又重新充满希望。</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">中国学术界到底有多腐败？</title><link href="https://huangjunye.github.io//2018/02/20/%E4%B8%AD%E5%9B%BD%E5%AD%A6%E6%9C%AF%E7%95%8C%E5%88%B0%E5%BA%95%E6%9C%89%E5%A4%9A%E8%85%90%E8%B4%A5%3F/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="中国学术界到底有多腐败？" /><published>2018-02-19T18:47:24+00:00</published><updated>2018-02-19T18:47:24+00:00</updated><id>https://huangjunye.github.io//2018/02/20/%E4%B8%AD%E5%9B%BD%E5%AD%A6%E6%9C%AF%E7%95%8C%E5%88%B0%E5%BA%95%E6%9C%89%E5%A4%9A%E8%85%90%E8%B4%A5%3F</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://huangjunye.github.io//2018/02/20/%E4%B8%AD%E5%9B%BD%E5%AD%A6%E6%9C%AF%E7%95%8C%E5%88%B0%E5%BA%95%E6%9C%89%E5%A4%9A%E8%85%90%E8%B4%A5%3F/">&lt;p&gt;这两天重新看了一遍亦明在2003年写的《中国学术界到底有多腐败？》。第一次这篇文章时大概是十年多以前，我还是初中生。那时候我对大学充满了期待，觉得大学是个很神圣的地方，可以得到很多大师的指点，学到很多其他地方学习不到的知识。那时候我听说大学很大，课间换教室要骑自行车。因为我妈上过大学，所以我就那天抓着她问大学究竟有多大，是不是大得要骑自行车。大学之大，指的当然不是校园有多大，大楼有多高，而是大师有多少。初中时看的这篇文章，打破了我对大学种种美好的幻想。它让我意识到大学并不是一个神圣而完美的地方。恰恰相反，大学里暗藏着各种腐败见不得人的东西。后来，我又看了覃彪喜写的《读大学，究竟读什么？》，对中国大学的真实情况有了更深入的了解。我对中国大学从向往渐渐变成希望。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;不过，我并没有多少机会去验证《腐败》一文跟《读大学》中描写的中国大学。高考成绩高不成低不就的我，上不了中科大，只能去华南理工。本想着一辈子待在广东，结果阴差阳错地拿到了新加坡政府奖学金，到了南洋理工读大学。在新加坡自然看不到中国大学那般的百生丑态。但是新加坡的学术界也不见得非常纯洁，大概欧美也如此？渐渐觉得小时候梦想的神圣象牙塔其实并不存在。大师，其实到哪里都是稀有动物。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;时隔多年再读《腐败》，有了不一样的感受。首先我不再全盘接受作者的观点，对他举的例子也仔细考察了一番。这文章的结构不是很清晰，论证也不严谨。常常快要说到点子上，却突然冒出一句，“不用说也知道”。另一方面，我对中国大学的腐败仍然感到失望。我查了一下文章里提到的腐败教授们，发现过了十几年，他们大多仍然逍遥法外。好几个退休、去世时，就职大学和科学院还撰文赞颂他们“为人师表”、“学术泰斗”云云。真正被抓的我只找到一个，就是褚健。13年被抓，17年被判三年三个月，减去审判期间的囚禁，审判后三天便被释放。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;不过近年来很多有海外科研经验的学者回国，特别是实施青年千人计划以来，每年都有几百上千的优秀学者回国。这些有海外经验的优秀学者必然也会把海外优秀的科研操守带回去。这样长期下去，国内学术界的腐败现象，虽然不可能完全摒除，但是必然会得到改善。希望再过十年再读《腐败》一文，会觉得大家都过虑了，一切都变好了。&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;hjunye&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;h.jun.ye@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Huang Junye&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>h.jun.ye@gmail.com</email></author><category term="科研" /><summary type="html">这两天重新看了一遍亦明在2003年写的《中国学术界到底有多腐败？》。第一次这篇文章时大概是十年多以前，我还是初中生。那时候我对大学充满了期待，觉得大学是个很神圣的地方，可以得到很多大师的指点，学到很多其他地方学习不到的知识。那时候我听说大学很大，课间换教室要骑自行车。因为我妈上过大学，所以我就那天抓着她问大学究竟有多大，是不是大得要骑自行车。大学之大，指的当然不是校园有多大，大楼有多高，而是大师有多少。初中时看的这篇文章，打破了我对大学种种美好的幻想。它让我意识到大学并不是一个神圣而完美的地方。恰恰相反，大学里暗藏着各种腐败见不得人的东西。后来，我又看了覃彪喜写的《读大学，究竟读什么？》，对中国大学的真实情况有了更深入的了解。我对中国大学从向往渐渐变成希望。 不过，我并没有多少机会去验证《腐败》一文跟《读大学》中描写的中国大学。高考成绩高不成低不就的我，上不了中科大，只能去华南理工。本想着一辈子待在广东，结果阴差阳错地拿到了新加坡政府奖学金，到了南洋理工读大学。在新加坡自然看不到中国大学那般的百生丑态。但是新加坡的学术界也不见得非常纯洁，大概欧美也如此？渐渐觉得小时候梦想的神圣象牙塔其实并不存在。大师，其实到哪里都是稀有动物。 时隔多年再读《腐败》，有了不一样的感受。首先我不再全盘接受作者的观点，对他举的例子也仔细考察了一番。这文章的结构不是很清晰，论证也不严谨。常常快要说到点子上，却突然冒出一句，“不用说也知道”。另一方面，我对中国大学的腐败仍然感到失望。我查了一下文章里提到的腐败教授们，发现过了十几年，他们大多仍然逍遥法外。好几个退休、去世时，就职大学和科学院还撰文赞颂他们“为人师表”、“学术泰斗”云云。真正被抓的我只找到一个，就是褚健。13年被抓，17年被判三年三个月，减去审判期间的囚禁，审判后三天便被释放。 不过近年来很多有海外科研经验的学者回国，特别是实施青年千人计划以来，每年都有几百上千的优秀学者回国。这些有海外经验的优秀学者必然也会把海外优秀的科研操守带回去。这样长期下去，国内学术界的腐败现象，虽然不可能完全摒除，但是必然会得到改善。希望再过十年再读《腐败》一文，会觉得大家都过虑了，一切都变好了。</summary></entry></feed>