<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Default on Junye Huang</title><link>https://huangjunye.github.io/categories/default/</link><description>Recent content in Default on Junye Huang</description><image><title>Junye Huang</title><url>https://huangjunye.github.io/profile-photo.jpg</url><link>https://huangjunye.github.io/profile-photo.jpg</link></image><generator>Hugo -- 0.145.0</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://huangjunye.github.io/categories/default/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>1D Quantum Random Walk</title><link>https://huangjunye.github.io/drafts/1d-quantum-random-walk/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://huangjunye.github.io/drafts/1d-quantum-random-walk/</guid><description>&lt;p>Introduction&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Quantum random walk (QRW) is the quantum version of the classical random walk. It would be easier to understand the quantum version, if you get a picture of the classical version. Imagine you are walking in a narrow street, in which you can only walk forwards or backwards. You are playing this random walk game. You toss a coin: if it's head, you walk one step forwards; if it's tail, you walk one step backwards. If you keep tossing and walking, you are essentially doing a classical random walk (CRW) (in 1 dimension). It's that simple. If you calculate the probability of your position after N steps, you will get a Gaussian distribution. Galton board is probably a more familiar example of CRW than the game I just mentioned. You can see the Youtube video below.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Edible Electronics</title><link>https://huangjunye.github.io/drafts/edible-electronics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://huangjunye.github.io/drafts/edible-electronics/</guid><description>&lt;p>Imagine a series of edible electronics&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Elon Musk</title><link>https://huangjunye.github.io/drafts/elon-musk/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://huangjunye.github.io/drafts/elon-musk/</guid><description>&lt;p>Recently, I have read a biography and a few excellent &lt;a href="http://waitbutwhy.com/2015/05/elon-musk-the-worlds-raddest-man.html">blogposts&lt;/a> on wait but why about Elon Musk. For those who don't know about Elon Musk, he is the most crazy entrepreneur in the world. He was a co-founder of a few Internet companies, including PayPal. He is currently running at the same time two of the most incredible startups in the world: SpaceX and Tesla Motor.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>SpaceX is awesome. It was founded by Elon at 2002, aiming to colonise Mars to make us, homo sapiens sapiens, a multi-planetary species. Through many years of struggles, SpaceX has designed its rocket engines and many other parts from ground up, making its rockets the cheapest yet one of the most powerful ones in history. Its rockets can be launched and return to the designate areas with accuracy of a few meters like science fiction. It has plans to send unmanned spacecrafts to Mars at 2018 and eventually send people to Mars as early as 2025.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Scientist, Engineer, or Entrepreneur?</title><link>https://huangjunye.github.io/drafts/scientist-engineer-or-entrepreneur-/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://huangjunye.github.io/drafts/scientist-engineer-or-entrepreneur-/</guid><description>&lt;p>Scientist, engineer, or entrepreneur?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This question has struck me many times in my life.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Scientist - Einstein, CN Yang&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Engineer - Nikola Tesla&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Entrepreneur - Steve Jobs&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What is a scientist&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What is an engineer&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What is an entrepreneur&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Scientist, engineer, or entrepreneur? Draft</title><link>https://huangjunye.github.io/drafts/scientist-engineer-or-entrepreneur-draft/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://huangjunye.github.io/drafts/scientist-engineer-or-entrepreneur-draft/</guid><description>&lt;p>Scientist, engineer, or entrepreneur?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This question has struck me many times in my life.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Two years ago, I found my notebook in primary school when I cleared my stuff of my room in my hometown. In the notebook, it was written "I want to become a scientist who devote himself to contributing to humanity." It was a surprise and joy to found this sentence, although it was merely a dream from a 10-year-old boy who didn't have a single idea what it took to become a scientist.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Spintronics</title><link>https://huangjunye.github.io/drafts/spintronics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://huangjunye.github.io/drafts/spintronics/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Visionary</title><link>https://huangjunye.github.io/drafts/visionary/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://huangjunye.github.io/drafts/visionary/</guid><description>&lt;p>Recently, I have read many articles about visionaries, including Elon Musk, Howard Hughes, Richard Branson and Craig Venter. I am not sure &lt;em>visionary&lt;/em> is the right word to describe them, but I am sure they all share some extraordinary characters: determination, leadership, creativity, and independent thinking.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>